The Eric Simon Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Eric Simon Papers
1938-1978
MSS 84
Yale University Music Library
1
(2 boxes)
Compositions and arrangements by the Austrian-American clarinetist and composer Eric Simon (1907-1984)
Simon, Eric, 1907-1994
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Eric Simon Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University in 1994 by the bequest of Eric Simon.
Arrangement
In 1 series: I. Music.
Scope and Contents
The Eric Simon Papers consist of scores and parts of manuscript and photocopied music, the majority of which are Simon's own musical compositions and arrangements. A short pedagogical work co-written by Simon is also included.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Vienna, Eric Simon (1907-1994) studied piano from the age of 8, and at the age of 14 he began studying the clarinet with Victor Polatschek, the principal clarinetist of the Vienna Philharmonic. Simon later studied with Polatschek's successor, Leopold Wlach. After spending one year in the Soviet Union, where he played in the Moscow Philharmonic, Simon subsequently held positions playing the clarinet in the Vienna State Opera orchestra and the Prades Festival Orchestra. In 1938 Simon left Europe for the United States, moving first to New York, and in 1949 settling in Sherman, Connecticut, where he maintained his home for the rest of his life. Following his move to the U.S., Simon played in the New York City Symphony under Leopold Stokowski and Leonard Bernstein.
In 1940 and 1941 Simon gave clarinet lessons to Benny Goodman, who had been recommended to Simon by John Hammond. Simon's work with Goodman was indicative of the esteem in which he was held by his musical colleagues, first in Europe and later in the United States. The list of friends with whom Simon carried on correspondence and musical collaborations constitutes a veritable who's who of twentieth-century music. An important collection of Simon's correspondence with composers, conductors, and other musicians now resides in the Music Library at the University of California, Los Angeles, under the shelf-mark Collection no. 128.
Throughout his teaching career, both in his private studio and at the Mannes School of Music and the New School, Simon insisted that students of all ages be engaged with the best musical models possible, and he often created his own transcriptions and arrangements to facilitate such interactions. Simon's musical transcriptions also show an abiding love of the Viennese masters Beethoven, Schubert, Strauss, and Brahms, whose music figures prominently both in this collection of manuscripts and in the several published editions of Simon's arrangements. In addition to his active career as a teacher and arranger, Simon also turned his attention on occasion to original composition. Of particular note in this collection are the original works for organ and choir that he composed in the 1970s for the First Congregational Church in New Milford, Connecticut.
Simon, Eric, 1907-1994
- Music, Series I
  - [Marches, band. Selections] 2 Märsche / L. van Beethoven., Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827; 15 manuscript parts (30 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Copyist's manuscript in ink.
    Contents: [WoO 18] -- [WoO 19]
    Parts for pic, flI-II, clI-III, bsnI-II, contra bsn, hnI-II, tptI-II, tbnIII, perc.
  - [Marches, piano, 4 hands, op. 45; arr.] Three marches for piano 4 hands / by Beethoven; orchestrated by Eric Simon., Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827; 1 manuscript score (23 p.); + 12 manuscript parts (32 p. total); 34 & 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    For pic, flI, obI/II, clI/II, bsnI/II, hnI/II, tptI/II, perc, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc/b.
  - [Wozzeck. Act 1. Militärmusik; arr.] Marsch aus Wozzeck / A. Berg, Berg, Alban, 1885-1935; 24 manuscript parts (29 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Copyist's manuscript in ink and colored pencil.
    Parts for pic, flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, hnI-II, tptI-II, tbnI-II, tba, perc.
  - [Ernste Gesänge; arr.] Vier ernste Gesänge, op. 121 / Brahms; orchestrated by Eric Simon., Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897; 1 manuscript score (56 p) + 11 manuscript parts (68 p. total); 35 & 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At end: New York, September 8, 1940.
    For: bass solo, flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, hnI-IV, tptI/II, tbnI/III, timp, vla, vc, b.
    Includes 2nd set of manuscript parts (37 p. total)
  - [Marches, E-flat major, WAB 116] Marsch / Anton Bruckner; eingerichtet von Franz Bürkhart., Bruckner, Anton, 1824-1896; 1 manuscript cond. score (4 p.) + 26 manuscript parts (26 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Parts for fl, ob, cl (B-flat) I-III, cl (E-flat), hnI-III, Piccolokornett, tptI-IV, FlügelhornI-II, TenorhornI-II, Basstrompete, bar, tbnI-II, bsI-II, perc.
  - [Good soldier Schweik. Suite; arr.] The good soldier Schweik, op. 32: suite / Robert Kurka., Kurka, Robert, 1921-1957; 7 p. of manuscript music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Arr. for piano.
  - [Symphonies pour petit orchestre. No. 5] 5e symphonie / D. Milhaud., Milhaud, Darius, 1892-1974; 10 manuscript parts (19 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    For pic, fl, ob, Eh, cl, b cl, bsnI-II, hnI-II.
  - [Balletti, woodwinds, horn, strings] Balletti a 9 / Jan Novák. -- Praha: eský hudební fond, 1958., Novák, Jan, 1921-; 9 parts (79 p. total); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    For fl, ob, cl, bsn, hn, vln, vla, vc, b.
  - [Lischen et Fritzchen], Offenbach, Jacques, 1819-1880; 1 manuscript score (50 p.) + 7 manuscript parts (53 p. total); 35 & 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Copyist's manuscript in ink, pencil, and colored pencil.
    Parts for fl, clI-II, bsn, hn, vln1 (1p. transposition only), vla (1p. transposition only)
  - [Lischen et Fritzchen. Vocal score], Offenbach, Jacques, 1819-1880; 1 manuscript vocal score (31 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Divertissement à la hongroise; arr.] Divertissement à la hongroise (Hungarian divertimento), op. 54 / Schubert; orchestral transcription by Eric Simon., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 manuscript score (56 p.) + 23 manuscript parts (79 p. total); 34 & 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Copyist's manuscript in ink and pencil.
    At end: S.S. Nieuw Amsterdam [14.V.1938 crossed out] May 14, 1938.
    For flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, hnI-IV, tptI-II, tbnI-II, b tbn, perc, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc, b.
  - [Divertissement à la hongroise; arr.] Divertissement à la hongroise (Hungarian divertimento), op. 54 / Franz Schubert; orchestral transcription by Eric Simon., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 manuscript score (34 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Abbreviated version.
    For flI/, obI/II, clI/II, bsnI/II, hnI/IV, tptI/II, tbnI/II, b tbn, perc, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc, b.
  - [Divertissement à la hongroise; arr.] Andante., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 manuscript score (27 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    For flI/, obI/II, clI/II, bsnI/II, hnI/IV, tptI/II, tbnI/II, b tbn, perc, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc, b, pno/cond.
  - [Divertissement à la hongroise; arr.] Divertissement à la hongroise (Hungarian divertimento), op. 54 / Franz Schubert; orchestral transcription by Eric Simon., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 manuscript condensed score (7 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Score for pno/cond.
  - [Grande marche funèbre; arr.] Trauermarsch / F. Schubert., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 13 manuscript parts (13 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Parts for flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, hn, tbnI-III, org.
  - [Marches militaires, piano, 4 hands, D. 733. No. 3; arr.] Military march E-flat / Schubert; trans. Eric Simon., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 manuscript score (11 p.) + 28 manuscript parts (48 p. total); 35 & 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Lacks hnI part.
    For pic, flI-II, obI-II, clI-IV, bsnI-II, contra bsn, hnI-IV, tptI-IV, tbnI-III, tba, perc.
  - [Variationen über ein Original-Thema, piano, 4 hands, D. 813, A-flat major; arr.] Variationen in As-dur, op. 35 (für Klavier zu vier Händen) / Schubert; für Orchester gesetzt von Erich Simon. -- [Wien]: Ringbuchhandlung-Gesellschaft, 1937., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 18 parts (68 p.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Parts for flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, hnI-II, tptI-II, timp, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc, b.
  - [Disillusion] Disillusion / words [by] Langston Hughes; music [by] Eric Simon., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Holograph in ink.
    For voice and piano.
  - [Disillusion] Disillusion / [words by] Langston Hughes; music [by] Eric Simon., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - [Disillusion. German] Erkenntnis., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - [Emilia Galotti. Final scene. Vocal score] Emilia Galotti: opera: letzte Szene = last scene / by Eric Simon., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript vocal score (17 p.); 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Photocopy of holograph.
    "Libretto adapted after the drama by G.E. Lessing, English translation [and] piano reduction by the composer."
  - [For whom the bell tolls] For whom the bell tolls / Eric Simon. -- New York: Alexander Broude, 1969., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 score (7 p.); 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    For SATB chorus a capella.
  - [Organ works (1977). Offertorium] Offertorium: variations on a theme by Beethoven / Eric Simon. -- c1977., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    At end: Sherman, Conn., Aug. 9, 1977.
  - [Organ works (1977). Postludium] Postludium for organ / Eric Simon. -- c1977., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (1 p.); 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - [Organ works (1977). Praeludium] Praeludium for organ / Eric Simon. -- c1977., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    At end: Sherman, Conn, Aug. 8, 1977.
  - [Organ works (1977) (sketches)], Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 8 manuscript p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Holograph in pencil.
  - [Psalm 1, chorus] The first psalm: as rhymed by Robert Burns / Eric Simon. -- c1977., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    At end: Sherman, Conn., July 29, 1977.
  - [Psalm 1, chorus (sketch)] The first psalm: as rhymed by Robert Burns / Eric Simon., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Holograph in ink and pencil.
  - [Te Deum] Te Deum / Eric Simon. -- c1978., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (18 p.) + 5 manuscript parts (15 p. total); 44 & 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Holograph in ink, and photocopy of copyist's manuscript
    "For the fiftieth birthday of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., who liberated his people peacefully, thereby helping to liberate his enemies."
    For SATB, cl, tpt, tbn, perc., b.
  - [Te Deum. Vocal score] Te Deum / Eric Simon. -- c1978., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript vocal score (24 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Photocopy of copyist's manuscript
    At end: Sherman, Conn., March 23, 1978.
  - [Toccata in tempore belli civilis] Toccata in tempore belli civilis / Eric Simon., Simon, Eric, 1907-1994; 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    For organ.
  - [Nocturne, band, op. 34, C major] Notturno, op. 34 / L. Spohr., Spohr, Louis, 1784-1859; 16 manuscript parts (71 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Parts for fl/pic, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, corno di basso & contra bsn, corno di posta, hnI-II, tptI-II, tbn, triangle, tamburo gr. & piatti.
  - [Suites, flute, piano, op. 737] A suite for flute or violin with piano accompaniment, op. 737 / by Robert Stolz. -- c1943., Stolz, Robert, 1880-1975; 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - [Suites, flute, piano, op. 737. Autumn memories; arr.] Autumn memories / R. Stolz; orch. E. Simon., Stolz, Robert, 1880-1975; 1 manuscript score (3 p.) + 8 manuscript parts (9 p. total); 34 & 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    For fl, cl, vlnI, vlnII, vla, vc, b, pno.
  - [Suites, flute, piano, op. 737. Rainbow bubbles; arr.] Rainbow bubbles / Robert Stolz; orch. E. Simon., Stolz, Robert, 1880-1975; 1 manuscript score (4 p.) + 8 manuscript parts (9 p. total); 34 & 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - [Radetzky-Marsch; arr.] Radetzkymarsch, op. 228 / J. Strauss (elder), Strauss, Johann, 1804-1849; 1 manuscript score (8 p.) + 27 manuscript parts (53 p. total); 35 & 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Parts for pic, flI-II, obI-II, cl in AI-II, cl in B-flatI-II, bsnI-II, contra bsn, hnI-IV, tptI-IV, tbnI-III, tba, perc.
  - [Suites, woodwinds, horns (4), op. 4, B-flat major] Suite, op. 4 / R. Strauss., Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949; 13 manuscript parts (122 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Parts for flI-II, obI-II, clI-II, bsnI-II, contra bsn/tba, hnI-IV.
  - First steps in music: a new approach to music for beginners of all ages / by Ruth Edwards and Eric Simon. -- New York: Edward B. Marks Music Corp., 1948., 32 p.; 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Pl. no.: 12605-29